<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-25T12:28:35+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">David Hutchinson</title><subtitle>Postdoctoral Researcher in Paleoclimate Modelling, Stockholm University</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Procrastination vs Busyness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/12/05/procrastination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procrastination vs Busyness" /><published>2018-12-05T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-05T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/12/05/procrastination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/12/05/procrastination.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I started this blog was an inspiration from an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uow.edu.au/~bmartin/pubs/09aur.pdf&quot;&gt;research productivity&lt;/a&gt;. This article argues that writing quality and productivity is improved greatly by doing small chunks regularly. So each blog post is a small piece of work that allows me to test out some ideas without creating too much pressure or time drain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this concept comes from a 1989 study called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0005796789901447&quot;&gt;Procrastination, busyness and bingeing&lt;/a&gt;. Incidentally, that article provides some bitingly accurate commentary on academic life. It suggests that one of the warning signs of procrastination is to display one’s busyness. And that the antidote to procrastination (at least when it comes to writing) is to work regularly in small chunks, with some socially enforced accountability. A really interesting finding for me was that of perceived priority. They found that the ‘procrastinators’ tended to report that writing was a &lt;strong&gt;high priority&lt;/strong&gt;, whereas those who made regular progress reported that writing was a &lt;strong&gt;moderate priority&lt;/strong&gt;. The implication is that part of the reason we procrastinate is because we build something up in our heads and make it seem scarier than it really is. Then once we start to make progress, we realise it’s not that big a deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that I have struggled at times with procrastination during my career and studies, and at times I certainly have engaged in ‘busyness displays’. But then again, I really am very busy a lot of the time, because I have a lot to do! So what’s the difference between genuinely being fully occupied and thus having to delay something, and procrastinating? I suspect the answer is a bit subjective, and can only be properly answered through context and honestly assessing one’s important goals. Procrastination is defined as a &lt;em&gt;needless and voluntary delay&lt;/em&gt; on an important goal or project, despite knowing that this delay is harming you (see Pychyl’s book below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great resource I’ve found on this subject is a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Solving-Procrastination-Puzzle-Concise-Strategies-ebook/dp/B00DGZKJ3Y&quot;&gt;Solving the procrastination puzzle&lt;/a&gt;, by Timothy Pychyl. It’s a concise and well researched analysis, which presents some excellent strategies to combat procrastination. He coins some handy mantras, such as “I won’t feel more like doing it tomorrow” and “Just get started”, i.e. straight to the point and practical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from prescriptive strategies to solve the problem, it’s also important to acknowledge that often, procrastination is caused by anxiety. Facing up to one’s anxiety around a big and scary thing is often the hardest and most important challenge in solving the problem of procrastination. The strategy outlined above, writing in small chunks, is a form of &lt;em&gt;progressive desensitisation&lt;/em&gt;. Repeated exposure in small doses helps to lower one’s fear, making it easier over time. I think procrastination is something that I’ll always be working on in some way or another, because it’s a natural human tendency and is rooted in emotions that can never be exercised away. But I do think I can learn to manage it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of the reasons why I started this blog was an inspiration from an article on research productivity. This article argues that writing quality and productivity is improved greatly by doing small chunks regularly. So each blog post is a small piece of work that allows me to test out some ideas without creating too much pressure or time drain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/08/13/deep-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Work" /><published>2018-08-13T15:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-13T15:20:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/08/13/deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/08/13/deep-work.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read a book by Cal Newport called Deep Work. I was inspired to read it after seeing his excellent article in the New York Times about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/20/jobs/quit-social-media-your-career-may-depend-on-it.html&quot;&gt;quitting social media&lt;/a&gt;.  Newport coins the term “deep work” to describe tasks that require highly focused, uninterrupted attention for long periods of time. This kind of work produces things that are &lt;em&gt;rare and valuable&lt;/em&gt;. Deep work typically requires expert knowledge that takes years to fully develop, and therefore can’t be replicated easily by someone else. He contrasts this with &lt;em&gt;shallow work&lt;/em&gt;, which describes tasks that are of a networking or logistical nature, that can be performed while somewhat distracted, and are easy to replicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be said, this book is of the personal development variety, and therefore must be read with a healthy dose of detachment and skepticism. That said, Deep Work was an illuminating read and contained many suggestions that I want to try. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time blocking:&lt;/strong&gt; Draw on a piece of lined paper the hours in your forthcoming work day, separated into half hour blocks, and actively plan what you will do with half-hour of your day. That forces you to think carefully about what you ought to be spending your time on, and develop a realistic idea of how long a given task will actually take. Revise and re-plan as much as necessary, but the idea is that creating a plan is a lot better than having no plan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do email / internet in planned chunks:&lt;/strong&gt; Set aside clear blocks of time in which you will process your emails. This might be once an hour for 10 minutes, or it might be twice a day for 20-30 minutes. Or if promptly responding to emails is a high proirity, you could do it more frequently. But the key is to limit it to discrete blocks and be strict about those blocks. That way you create time for more important work outside those blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a deep work routine:&lt;/strong&gt; Newport cites many examples of successful authors or researchers who have a set block of time (e.g. 2-3 hours at the beginning of each work day) for doing deep work. The idea is to train yourself into having a set period and environment where you work at your most intense concentration. He also stresses that most people have a deep work limit of around 4 hours per day. Outside of that, you’re simply too tired and can’t sustain it. So structure your day to enable those hours so they don’t get eaten my distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quit social media:&lt;/strong&gt; This one is controversial and plenty of my friends don’t agree on this. The reasons are straightforward: social media is addictive, fragments your attention and actively damages your ability to think deeply. So it’s detrimental to doing research, and therefore does harm to me professionally. We can easily identify what we gain from social media, such as connections with people far away, getting in touch with old friends, hearing about good stories, etc. But using social media often does insidious damage to our concentration skills, and actually doesn’t help us to make &lt;em&gt;close friendships&lt;/em&gt;. Close friendships are built upon spending time together in person, and making an effort for one another. Social media requires negligible effort, hence it really only builds networks of &lt;em&gt;loose acquaintances&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enforce strict limits to your work time:&lt;/strong&gt; This is also a bold suggestion to anyone in academia, as it goes against the engrained culture of &lt;em&gt;going the extra mile&lt;/em&gt; (workaholism). But he argues quite effectively that limiting one’s work time to reasonable hours (i.e. 8 hours a day) can increase your productivity, because it forces you to spend your time wisely. Having adequate rest also means you return to work with energy and a fresh mind, rather than being jaded and exhausted on a regular basis. It also forces you to work with &lt;em&gt;intensity and focus&lt;/em&gt;, rather than slowly and distractedly. I like this philosophy and I want to follow it as best I can.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn’t like about the book was that Newport slipped in to bragging a little too often about how successful he is. This is an annoying but very common feature of personal development books. It’s like: I need to prove to you that my ideas will change your life for the better so I’m going to tell you how awesome I am. I find myself questioning whether his claims are too good to be true. But objectively, his track record as a researcher is fantastic, he has published 5 books already in a young career, and he claims not to work overtime. So I will forgive him his overconfidence if his methods actually end up helping me. But I know that at some level, what truly works for me will always be a little different to what I’ve read in a book like this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently read a book by Cal Newport called Deep Work. I was inspired to read it after seeing his excellent article in the New York Times about quitting social media. Newport coins the term “deep work” to describe tasks that require highly focused, uninterrupted attention for long periods of time. This kind of work produces things that are rare and valuable. Deep work typically requires expert knowledge that takes years to fully develop, and therefore can’t be replicated easily by someone else. He contrasts this with shallow work, which describes tasks that are of a networking or logistical nature, that can be performed while somewhat distracted, and are easy to replicate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new model of the late Eocene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/07/17/eocene-control.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new model of the late Eocene" /><published>2018-07-17T13:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-17T13:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/07/17/eocene-control</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/07/17/eocene-control.html">&lt;p&gt;We have recently published a new set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5194/cp-2018-52&quot;&gt;climate model simulations for the late Eocene&lt;/a&gt;. This model uses paleogeography and boundary conditions from 38 million years ago, just before the Eocene-Oligocene transition. We found that under these boundary conditions, the Arctic Ocean was very fresh at the surface. This fresh water spilled over into the North Atlantic, making it very light and unable to form deep water masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/EOT_ctl_state.png&quot; width=&quot;90%&quot; align=&quot;centre&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ocean has deep water forming in the North Pacific and the Southern Ocean. This is very different from the modern ocean, where northern sinking occurs in the North Atlantic instead of the North Pacific. This change is due to freshwater forcing at the surface: a combination of precipitation, evaporation and runoff. These factors combine with changes to the paleogeography to make the North Pacific saltier than today. This sinking pattern is consistent with Eocene proxy records of deep water formation, identified by &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2013PA002535&quot;&gt;Neodymium tracers&lt;/a&gt;. The very fresh Arctic Ocean of around 20 psu is also consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature04692&quot;&gt;Eocene proxy information&lt;/a&gt;, although it gets more unclear around the Eocene-Oligocene transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Fig07_moc.png&quot; width=&quot;90%&quot; align=&quot;centre&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model was a long time coming. It took something like two years of experimenting, testing, failing and fixing things to eventually get publishable results. (Two years was the entire length of my original postdoc position.) The simulations themselves are run for 6500 years and are still not in equilibrium. This is a perennial issue, but we are trying to examine it thoroughly and hopefully come up with faster ways of reaching equilibrium next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We have recently published a new set of climate model simulations for the late Eocene. This model uses paleogeography and boundary conditions from 38 million years ago, just before the Eocene-Oligocene transition. We found that under these boundary conditions, the Arctic Ocean was very fresh at the surface. This fresh water spilled over into the North Atlantic, making it very light and unable to form deep water masses.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visit to Utrecht</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/05/11/visit-to-utrecht.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visit to Utrecht" /><published>2018-05-11T14:08:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-11T14:08:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/05/11/visit-to-utrecht</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/05/11/visit-to-utrecht.html">&lt;p&gt;Just had a really nice 1 week visit to the Institute for Marine and Atmospheric Research, Utrecht (IMAU), working on collaborations with Michiel Baatsen and Anna von der Heydt. I really enjoyed the stay, and the whole group was really welcoming. Had my first taste of commuting to work by bicycle, Dutch-style. This was an eye-opener: heavy bike traffic, requiring constant vigilance and consideration of the multiple streams of riders crammed into narrow lanes. You definitely feel a safety in numbers that is hard to replicate anywhere else in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fun aside, Michiel and I made a video of the plate tectonic evolution from 64 Ma to present:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FR49W9YzqmQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This displays only modern day topography on top of plate tectonic motion - there are no reconstructions of actual paleoelevations or shorelines. But it’s fun to watch, and unlike many plate tectonic videos I’ve seen, it has a really high frame rate! The continents really look like they are gliding rather than iteratively jumping from frame to frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could also dig a bit more into getting the missing seafloor depths, and focusing on the South Pole for instance. But it’s a nice start.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Just had a really nice 1 week visit to the Institute for Marine and Atmospheric Research, Utrecht (IMAU), working on collaborations with Michiel Baatsen and Anna von der Heydt. I really enjoyed the stay, and the whole group was really welcoming. Had my first taste of commuting to work by bicycle, Dutch-style. This was an eye-opener: heavy bike traffic, requiring constant vigilance and consideration of the multiple streams of riders crammed into narrow lanes. You definitely feel a safety in numbers that is hard to replicate anywhere else in the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Growing out of impostor syndrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/04/16/impostor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Growing out of impostor syndrome" /><published>2018-04-16T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/04/16/impostor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/issues/2018/04/16/impostor.html">&lt;p&gt;As a researcher in a fiercely competitive academic environment, you hear a lot of discussion about impostor syndrome. This is a mindset where success makes you feel like a fake. It’s when your internal belief system tells you that you are not worthy of your position, and sooner or later your colleagues and the world will realise that you are not up to the job. In many cases it leads to self-sabotage. Like not grabbing opportunities or applying for jobs and grants because you believe yourself to be inferior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have read a number of articles about impostor syndrome in journals like Nature and Science, as well as science blogs. I must admit, for a long time I didn’t really connect with them. I certainly had issues of self-doubt from time to time, but the articles I read didn’t strike me as being terribly useful. It wasn’t that I had nothing in common with the ‘impostors’, it was just that I didn’t see what I could gain from reading these stories. There seemed to be a fatalism about the way people described impostor syndrome. It was like: “I suffer from self-doubt and impostor feelings, it’s always been like this, it’s problematic for my career, etc.” The only solace to be found was that many people suffer this way, so it normalizes the feeling and the suffering. That’s a worthy message, but I couldn’t see how it was going to help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://bethrogerson.com/tag/imposter-syndrome/&quot;&gt;this blog by a therapist, Beth Rogerson&lt;/a&gt;. And for the first time I realised that there are in fact ways of overcoming it. This became much more interesting to me once I could actually see ways of not just ‘suffering together’ with other impostors, but really overcoming it. Having an action plan also made it easier for me to admit to myself that I did in fact suffer from impostor syndrome! (Side note: I really do!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprising news to me was a simple difference in mindset that separated impostors from non-impostors. They had a different view of intelligence. To paraphrase from Beth Rogerson’s blog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impostors saw &lt;em&gt;intelligence as fixed&lt;/em&gt;. They focused on performance goals, and saw success or failure on a task as a test of their intelligence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-impostors saw intelligence as &lt;em&gt;something that could grow&lt;/em&gt;. That meant that both success and failure can be viewed as a learning exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It struck me that this is an incredibly simple change in perspective. It’s so simple that it seems like it shouldn’t even matter. But when you think about it, it makes a lot of sense. If you feel like your intelligence is fixed, that you’ll never be any smarter than you are now, then a failure will seem like an insurmountable barrier (if you aren’t smart enough now, then you’ll never be). If you think your intelligence can grow, then even if you really suck at something now, you may one day be able to master it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually a really exciting idea to think that I could be more intelligent when I’m 40 or 50 than when I was 25 or 30. This certainly runs counter to what I believed. I learned at school that your brain power is strongest when you’re young, peaks at about 25 and then slowly wanes. I thought that getting older would bring more experience and knowledge, but not intelligence. But if it’s true, and we can all get smarter as we get older… That would be really cool.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As a researcher in a fiercely competitive academic environment, you hear a lot of discussion about impostor syndrome. This is a mindset where success makes you feel like a fake. It’s when your internal belief system tells you that you are not worthy of your position, and sooner or later your colleagues and the world will realise that you are not up to the job. In many cases it leads to self-sabotage. Like not grabbing opportunities or applying for jobs and grants because you believe yourself to be inferior.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First grant proposal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/04/16/proposal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First grant proposal" /><published>2018-04-16T16:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T16:30:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/04/16/proposal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/04/16/proposal.html">&lt;p&gt;I just submitted a proposal for a Formas mobility grant. This is my first ever grant proposal, so it’s a big step forward for me. If successful this would give me 3 years of postdoctoral funding, including 18 months on a visiting position in Bristol, and 18 months in Stockholm. Developing a thorough research plan for 3 years is a great exercise, and one that definitely does not come naturally to me. It’s very different to writing a paper, because you don’t have any results yet, and it’s about anticipating what will be a breakthrough in the future, and creating an exciting path towards discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a very different mindset. You have to follow your intuition to come up with an original idea. You have to convince yourself that your idea is really great and it’s really worth doing. Which is tricky if you tend to practice self-criticism, which is an important part of science in its own right. You have to put a lot of effort into writing a draft and then seeking lots of external feedback, because let’s face it, the first draft of anything always kind of sucks. And then you have to exercise judgment, as you get lots of constructive criticism, some of it going in contrary directions, and pull it all together into a polished argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s actually really cool to design your own research programme. You really do get to decide what’s the best avenue to pursue your next big breakthrough. And once you embark upon writing a proposal, it makes you a lot more open to picking up new suggestions and innovative ideas, whether it be from colleagues, friends or conferences. So whether the proposal succeeds or not, the act of writing one is a great way to focus your mind on what is the best thing to do next in your research.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I just submitted a proposal for a Formas mobility grant. This is my first ever grant proposal, so it’s a big step forward for me. If successful this would give me 3 years of postdoctoral funding, including 18 months on a visiting position in Bristol, and 18 months in Stockholm. Developing a thorough research plan for 3 years is a great exercise, and one that definitely does not come naturally to me. It’s very different to writing a paper, because you don’t have any results yet, and it’s about anticipating what will be a breakthrough in the future, and creating an exciting path towards discovery.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It takes forever to spin up a climate model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/02/09/spinup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It takes forever to spin up a climate model" /><published>2018-02-09T15:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-09T15:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/02/09/spinup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/paleoclimate/2018/02/09/spinup.html">&lt;p&gt;Climate models take thousands of years to equilibrate. This is a problem that has plagued ocean and climate modellers for decades, and there is no easy solution. To spin up a climate model means to initiate the ocean-atmosphere-land-ice system with some initial values, and then let it solve its physical equations of motion over and over until it reaches a steady state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with this is the ocean. The ocean has a very large heat capacity, it circulates very slowly, and interacts with the atmosphere only at the surface, while the deep remains rather isolated. So the temperature and salinity properties of the deep ocean can take thousands of years to adjust to new changes. According to one study &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/1520-0442%281996%29009%3C1092%3AATEIAG%3E2.0.CO%3B2&quot;&gt;it can take around 4000 years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normal procedure is to start the model with the best available observations of temperature and salinity, start simulating and then wait (usually a very long time) until it’s in equilibrium. When you’re dealing with the modern ocean, you  start from a position that is close to reality. I.e. Close to your intended outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This task is somewhat manageable when you are &lt;em&gt;only interested in simulating the ocean&lt;/em&gt;. The ocean evolves slowly, so you can take large time steps in your simulation. The forcing at the surface is held fixed, which means that the surface can reach near-equilibrium quickly, and the deep ocean can adjust towards a target that is not changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets more tricky when you couple the ocean to the atmosphere. The atmosphere by comparison moves very quickly, and needs much smaller time steps. So it takes a lot more resources to simulate the same block of time at the same resolution. You have to allow the ocean and atmosphere (and ice and land for that matter) to communicate with each other. You end up spending a lot more computing resources for each model year. Worse still, the ocean and atmopshere &lt;em&gt;feed back on each other&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ocean-only simulation might spin up in 2000 years, but try the same with an atmosphere, and you might that after all that time and adjustment, the atmosphere then wants to be colder. Or warmer. Or unstable because your model wasn’t designed for the reality you’re trying to recreate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re trying to simulate a climate from the deep past, this problem is compounded by the fact that you have very few observations to begin with. So you don’t know how close to reality you are when you begin, it’s hard to tell if you model is behaving well or not, and yet you know it will take a long time for your model to reach an equilibrium. You might run your model for 6 or 12 months, and then discover a problem, and have to start over.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Climate models take thousands of years to equilibrate. This is a problem that has plagued ocean and climate modellers for decades, and there is no easy solution. To spin up a climate model means to initiate the ocean-atmosphere-land-ice system with some initial values, and then let it solve its physical equations of motion over and over until it reaches a steady state.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New website created</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/12/08/new-website.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New website created" /><published>2017-12-08T15:11:20+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-08T15:11:20+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/12/08/new-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/12/08/new-website.html">&lt;p&gt;I finally joined the cool kids and created a github website. Style and panache will be added later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I finally joined the cool kids and created a github website. Style and panache will be added later.</summary></entry></feed>